Undergraduate Econometrics
Vanessa Berenguer-Rico
Description

The course is divided into two parts: (I) Microeconometrics and (II) Macroeconometrics.
Part I introduces some of the main tools used in microeconometric analyses. This part consists

of three main topics. The Örst one starts by motivating the statistical tools (data, concepts, meth-
ods, etc...) used in microeconometrics from a general perspective. Then, the linear regression model

under classical assumptions is reviewed. Methods developed to deal with situations in which classical

assumptions are not satisÖed are also considered. The second topic focuses on nonlinear models. Non-
linear estimation methods, such as non-linear least squares and maximum likelihood, are thoroughly

examined. The third topic applies these non-linear estimation methods to binary response and count
data models.

Part II motivates the main theoretical and empirical features that appear when dealing with macro-
economic data. This part consists of three main topics. The Örst one discusses why the analysis of

macroeconomic time series di§ers from the analysis of micro data. To that end, dependent and/or
heterogeneously distributed observations are introduced. The second topic focuses on the analysis of

univariate time series. In particular, stationary and non-stationary processes are studied. Special em-
phasis is given to autoregressive models. The third topic is devoted to the analysis of multivariate time

series. Single equation models are put forward. SpeciÖcally, autoregressive distributed lag models,
co-integrating relations and are discussed.

To deepen the understanding of the theoretical contents of the course as well as to familiarise you
with the analysis of real data, three computer lectures will be given by Felix Pretis (http://www.felixpretis.org/).
