Quantitative Economics and Econometrics
Aim:
To provide students with a thorough understanding of core techniques of quantitative economics and econometrics and their application to test economic theories and measure magnitudes relevant for economic policy. The course serves as a foundation for subsequent study of quantitative topics. The main focus will be on econometric methods that are useful to analyze individual level cross sectional data using OLS regression techniques.
Objectives:
At the end of the module, students should:
Understand the main techniques (most importantly, OLS regression) of quantitative economics and econometrics, including their strengths and limitations.
Understand how these techniques can be applied to test economic theories and measure economic magnitudes.
Have some practical experience of the application of econometric methods using Stata.

Jeffrey Wooldridge: Introductory Econometrics: Europe, Middle East, & Africa (EMEA) Edition, 1st edition.
Chapter 1 The Nature of Econometrics and Economic Data 1
PART 1: Regression Analysis with Cross-Sectional Data 21
Chapter 2 The Simple Regression Model 22
Chapter 3 Multiple Regression Analysis: Estimation 68
Chapter 4 Multiple Regression Analysis: Inference 118
Chapter 5 Multiple Regression Analysis: OLS Asymptotics 168
Chapter 6 Multiple Regression Analysis: Further Issues 186
Chapter 7 Multiple Regression Analysis with Qualitative
Information: Binary (or Dummy) Variables 227
Chapter 8 Heteroskedasticity 268
Chapter 9 More on Specification and Data Issues 303
PART 2: Regression Analysis with Time Series Data 343
Chapter 10 Basic Regression Analysis with Time Series Data 344
Chapter 11 Further Issues in Using OLS with Time Series Data 380
Chapter 12 Serial Correlation and Heteroskedasticity in Time Series Regressions 412
PART 3: Advanced Topics 447
Chapter 13 Pooling Cross Sections Across Time: Simple Panel Data Methods 448
Chapter 14 Advanced Panel Data Methods 484
Chapter 15 Instrumental Variables Estimation and Two Stage Least Squares 512
Chapter 16 Simultaneous Equations Models 554
Chapter 17 Limited Dependent Variable Models and Sample Selection Corrections 583
Chapter 18 Advanced Time Series Topics 632
Chapter 19 Carrying Out an Empirical Project